New political parties, a wild expansion
of federal power, and thousands of
common folk drunk off their gourd
wandering through the White House and
breaking furniture. Well, that must mean
we're in the age of Andrew Jackson,
baby. So, if you're ready to get them
brank cows milked, let's get to it. So,
let's begin by stating the obvious,
namely that the election of Andrew
Jackson in 1828 marked a significant
turning point in national US politics.
Like, not only did he win office by
directly campaigning to the American
people, he believed that by his
election, he now represented the
interests of the American people. And
just in case that last sentence didn't
fully wake up your emotional goblins
whose job it is to turn on your anxiety
sweats, keep in mind that
constitutionally it was Congress that
represented the people's voice. See, the
framers understood the president as the
servant of Congress. And in many ways,
that's how George Washington, who often
deferred to Congress, carried out his
terms in office. But Jackson believed
the people wanted him to be their
representative and therefore his
presidency was marked by a significant
expansion of executive power. Oh, and by
the way, if you want note guys to follow
along with this video and all my videos,
check that link in the description.
Furthermore, the Jackson presidency was
also a turning point because of several
other factors. First, he changed how
campaigns were run. You see, this
election occurred right at the same time
that many states were lowering or
abandoning property qualifications for
voting. And so, with universal white
male suffrage becoming the norm, a whole
lot more common folk were able to vote.
And Jackson, by all measures, understood
this assignment way better than his
opponent, John Quincy Adams. And Adams,
marvelous diplomat and statesman, though
he was, inhabited the old school of
thought that said that presidential
candidates should not campaign on their
own behalf. Instead, Adams believed that
he should wait off to the side and if
the country wanted him, they could come
and find him. But Jackson was like,
"Hey, hold my hard cider. Watch this."
And he and his team organized rallies
and nationwide campaign stops where
Jackson styled himself as a populist who
really understood the concerns of the
common white man. And while Adams was
locked away in his study reading dusty
old books in French, Jackson was busy
persuading the crap out of the new
expanded electorate. And then the second
momentous feature of Jackson's
presidency is that his election
represented a fundamental geographical
shift in electoral politics. You see,
every president before him was either
from Virginia or Massachusetts. In other
words, all those other presidents had a
closet full of fancy pants. But Jackson
was a frontier man born in the
Carolinas, but came of age in the
backwoods of Tennessee. And that meant
that he was the first president to be
elected from the western frontier area
of the United States. And that was kind
of a big deal because it reflected the
way universal white male suffrage was
changing the way presidential candidates
were chosen. Anyway, by the 1820s and
1830s, two rival political parties had
crystallized. You had the Democrats led
by Andrew Jackson. And this party was
the direct descendant of the
Jeffersonian Democratic Republicans. And
that means the Democrats wanted much of
what Jefferson wanted, namely a lassair
federal government whose main
characteristics were frugality and
staying out of people's business. And
then you had the Wigs led by our boy
Henry Clay. And this party was the
direct descendant of the now defunct
Federalist Party in the style of
Alexander Hamilton. And to be clear, the
formal emergence of the Wigs into US
national politics occurred later in
preparation for the election of 1840.
But regardless, the Wigs wanted a
stronger federal government that
involved itself with sponsoring a
national bank and funding for internal
infrastructure projects like roads and
bridges and canals. Okay, so enough of
all that. Now we need to consider the
ways in which Jackson expanded federal
power and the bitter debates that such
expansion caused. And there were three
big issues. First, Jackson expanded
federal power as a result of the
nullification crisis in 1832 and 1833.
Now, I hope the word nullification
started tinkling a few of your memory
bells from unit 3 because we're about to
make a juicy transun connection. So,
hopefully you remember that in response
to the Alien and Sedition Act, two
states passed the Virginia and Kentucky
resolutions which argued that states had
the right to nullify or, you know, like
not obey federal laws that they
considered unconstitutional. Well,
something eerily similar happened during
Jackson's presidency. So, the debate was
about the tariff of 1828, which was
passed under John Quincy Adams's
administration, and it was a doozy of
attack since it raised prices on
imported goods by 60%. And that was real
bad for Southerners because they relied
on imported goods on account of their
economy was dominated by agriculture.
You might even say this tax terrified
them.
Economic policy dad joke. Nailed it.
Anyway, Southerners hated this tax so
much that they referred to it as the
tariff of abominations. So, you know,
sounds like they were kind of neutral
about it. The point is southerners
assumed that once Jackson took office,
he would lead Congress to abolish the
tariff and score a win for the South.
However, northern states benefited from
this tariff and was home to many Jackson
supporters as well. And so, being in
such a political pickle, Jackson did
nothing about the tariff. And as it
turned out, such a move enraged his own
vice president, John C. Calhoun, who
himself was a South Carolina man. And as
a result, Calhoun encouraged South
Carolina to nullify this law because by
their reckoning, it clearly exceeded the
constitutional boundaries of federal
power. And then things got worse after a
couple years when Congress with
Jackson's support passed the tariff of
1832 which extended the same high tariff
rates for another four years. So in
response, South Carolina issued an
ordinance of nullification which
declared that the state would not
collect federal import tax revenue and
that if the federal authorities
attempted to override their ordinance,
South Carolina would go ahead and secede
from the union. And this is what became
known as the nullification crisis. Now
Jackson took pride in being a war hero
and he had no patience for sassy
recalcitrant nullifying nonsense. So
after Jackson was reelected in 1832, he
expanded federal power by leading
Congress to pass the Force Bill, which
gave Jackson authority to send federal
troops to South Carolina in order to
collect the taxes. In other words, if a
measly state was bold enough to
challenge the great Andrew Jackson, then
he was going to send the soldiers down
there to smack the nullification talk
right out of their mouth. But to be
fair, in threatening said smackdown,
Jackson also agreed to work with
Congress to get the tariff rate lowered,
which he was able to do. And in that
way, South Carolina was able to back
down from its threats while still saving
face. But the outcome was clear. Federal
power had won the day. But in order to
throw one last jab at the beefy federal
monster, the South Carolina legislature
passed a resolution nullifying the force
bill, which was kind of petty, but also
kind of awesome. Okay. Now, the second
way Jackson expanded federal power was
during a development known as the bank
war. So, just before the election of
1832, the charter for the second bank of
the United States was up for renewal,
and Jackson aimed to veto that charter.
And he branded the national bank as a
monster that benefited elites and harmed
ordinary Americans. And that wasn't that
hard of a cell since the economic
hardship of the panic of 1819 still
lingered in recent memory. Anyway,
Jackson's opponents in Congress hoped
that Jackson's veto would weaken his
chances in the upcoming election of
1832. But it in fact had the opposite
effect by framing the veto as a move
that protected the interest of common
farmers and laborers. Jackson enjoyed a
massive wave of support from these
people. And soon after his veto, the
Second Bank of the United States closed
its doors since Jackson refused to
deposit federal funds into its vault and
instead deposited them across several
other banks in states that were loyal to
Jackson. And that's why his opponents
called these Jackson's pet banks. It was
a major expansion of the president's
power because he single-handedly
determined the domestic economic policy
for the United States. And finally,
third, Jackson expanded federal power by
means of his efforts to remove American
Indians from their ancestral lands. Now
remember that Jackson gained his war
hero reputation first as an Indian
fighter during the seminal wars in
Florida. And so once he became
president, he was eager to help state
governments in Georgia, Florida, and the
Carolas and Illinois to remove the
American Indians from their own borders.
And the most notorious example was the
Indian Removal Act of 1830. And we're
going to focus specifically on the
Cherokee people of Georgia. Now, of all
the American Indian groups that lived
within the borders of the United States,
arguably it was the Cherokee who ought
to have been the best protected from
removal policies. And that's because
under the leadership of their chief,
John Ross, the Cherokee adopted the
policy of assimilation, which meant that
they believed their best means of
self-preservation was to adopt the
trappings of American culture. For
example, they had written themselves a
constitution that formed a Republican
style government on the model of the
United States. They also learned English
and dressed in American style clothing.
But once gold was discovered on their
land, Georgians got real hungry to move
on in and get rich. And so, John Ross
reached out to Jackson and tried to
convince him to recognize Cherokee
sovereignty. But Jackson responded by
leading Congress to pass the Indian
Removal Act. And under this law, the
Cherokee, as well as several other
American Indian groups, would be forced
to exchange their land in various states
for land in the unorganized territory
west of the Mississippi River. Now, in
this particular case, the Cherokee
resisted such policies and they did so
through the American court system. And
eventually, their plea came before the
Supreme Court in a case called Worooster
v. Georgia. And it might shock you to
learn that the court sided with the
Cherokee and upheld their sovereignty in
their own lands. Remember, Jackson
believed that he represented the will of
the people, and what the people of
Georgia wanted was the removal of the
Cherokee. So, Jackson refused to execute
the court's ruling and made plans for
Cherokee removal anyway, which began in
1838. It was a thousand-mile march that
became known as the Trail of Tears
because of the harsh conditions that led
to thousands of deaths along the way.
However, in other cases, American
Indians resisted removal by means of
violence, as they did in the Blackhawk
War of 1832. So in that year, Jackson
sent federal troops into western
Illinois to force the Sock and Fox
nations to move westward. Their chief,
Blackhawk, retreated into the Wisconsin
territory and then gathered a thousand
fighters to meet the US troops at a
place called Bad Axe. The result was a
massacre of the American Indians and the
force removal of the survivors. Okay, so
clearly Jackson was a glutton for
federal power and didn't seem to care
who he mowed down in order to get what
he believed was best for America, which
in many ways was really what was best
for him. But in all fairness, there are
a couple of examples where Jackson
actually did not make use of federal
power, but instead restrained himself.
First was regarding the debate about
federally funded internal improvements
to the United States. For example, the
bill that authorized the construction of
funding of the interstate Cumberland
Road was signed by Thomas Jefferson, but
since it was a massive project, it took
several decades to finish. The National
Republicans and later the Wigs approved
of federal spending on this interstate
road because it would both facilitate
westward migration and help connect
western farmers to eastern markets. But
the Democrats led by Jackson invoked the
fear of growing federal power at the
expense of the state. They believed an
interstate road would be
unconstitutional because the
constitution did not explicitly grant
that power to Congress. And then the
second major example of restraint from
Jackson was the question of the
annexation of Texas. So by 1821, the
Mexicans had successfully rebelled
against the Spanish and become an
independent state. And one of their main
problems was the abundance of Comanche
raids in the Northern Territory. So
their solution was to invite westward
migrating Americans to settle in the
Texas territory. And even though Mexico
had abolished slavery, they made a
special exception for American planters
looking to bring slavery with them into
the territory. However, Americans be
Americans, and it was soon apparent that
the settlers were in no way interested
in respecting the rules the Mexican
government gave them as conditions for
their settlement. And soon, because the
Texas plants contained such good soil
for planting, the American migrants
began to demand independence from Mexico
and later started a war of independence.
Now, long story short, under the
leadership of Sam Houston, Texas rebels
won the war with financial help from the
US federal government and Texas became
an independent nation. And Jackson,
though, he did long to admit Texas into
the United States exhibited caution
because he didn't want to start a war
with Mexico by either recognizing Texan
independence or by hinting at plans to
annex the new state. And since he was
finishing his second term and would be
leaving office, he didn't want the
debate about Texas to split his party
going into the 1836 election. though
Congress passed a gag rule which forbade
them from considering the Texas
question, particularly the slavery
question until after the election. But
even with those two examples of
restraint aside, there is no doubt that
the presidency of Andrew Jackson led to
a massive expansion of federal power and
a turning point that will forever change
presidential politics. Okay, you can
click here to watch my other videos on
unit 4, or you can click here to grab my
video note guides, which are going to
help you get all the content of this
course firmly crammed into your
brainful. I'm glad you came around and
I'll catch you on the flip-flop. I'm
lur.